Ewa Magdalena Nowara, Ph.D.

Baltimore, MD 21218 | enowara1@jhu.edu | https://ewanowara.github.io/ | LinkedIn

SUMMARY

Strong experience in leading research and product development in Computer Vision and Deep Learning. Published over 10 publications in top tier vision and machine learning venues. Owner of two patents. Three years of industry research experience in Microsoft Research and Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories. Passionate about my research having an impact on products to improve people's quality and enjoyment of life.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering

August 2015 - May 2021

Rice University, Houston, TX

Thesis: Imaging Photoplethysmography in Unconstrained Settings

Master of Science in Electrical and Computer Engineering

August 2015 - May 2018

Rice University, Houston, TX

Bachelor of Science in Physics

August 2011 - May 2015

St. Mary's University, San Antonio, TX

GPA: 4.0/4.0 (summa cum laude, Presidential Award Recipient)

RELEVANT SKILLS

Programming: Python, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, MATLAB, HTML/CSS, OpenCV, Docker, Arduino, Shell Expertise In: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Signal Processing, Optimization, Image Processing Experience In: Illustrator, 3D Printing, Soldering, Optics, Linux, Windows

Competencies: Strong interpersonal skills, excellent communicator, team player, data analytical skills, detail-oriented

RESEARCH AND WORK EXPERIENCE

Johns Hopkins University

May 2021 - Present

Postdoctoral Research Fellow in Electrical and Computer Engineering, Baltimore, MD

Mentor: Prof. Rama Chellappa

- Building computer vision and machine learning algorithms for geo-localization from a single RGB image in a classification setting, including Transformer, Resnet, and Triplet Network architectures
- Designing multi-modal models leveraging both RGB images and corresponding semantic segmentation maps to improve the model's invariance to appearance changes

Los Alamos National Laboratory

October 2020 - February 2021

Research Intern (Theoretical Division, T-5), Los Alamos, NM

Mentor: Brendt Wohlberg

Developed Encoder-Decoder and Long-Short-Term Memory (LSTM) architectures to reconstruct high resolution images obtained from multiple ptychographic measurements without access to ground truth

Microsoft Research June 2019 - June 2020

Research Intern (Human Understanding and Empathy Team), Redmond, WA

Mentors: Daniel McDuff, Mary Czerwinski

- Built a novel Convolutional Attention Neural Network to denoise temporal intensity signals from video
- Created realistic 3D avatars using computer graphics and physiological signals obtained from video
- Recovered physiological intensity variations from heavily compressed videos using supervised deep learning

Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories

May 2017 - June 2019

Research Intern (Computer Vision Team), Cambridge, MA

Mentors: Tim Marks, Hassan Mansour

Collaboratively designed a driver monitoring system using a joint design of hardware and algorithms

- Built a hardware system by using RGB and NIR cameras, optical and 3D printed components, light sources synchronized with camera frame capture
- Developed optimization and signal processing algorithms using Robust Principal Components Analysis (RPCA), Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers (ADMM), Fast Iterative Shrinkage-Thresholding Algorithm (FISTA), face detection, tracking
- Collected and released the first large public driving dataset with face videos and physiology

SELECTED RECENT PUBLICATIONS (Full list on Google Scholar)

- 1. **Nowara, E. M.**, McDuff, D., Veeraraghavan, A. "The Benefit of 'Distraction': Denoising Video-Based Physiological Measurements using Inverse Attention" *ICCV*, 2021
- 2. **Nowara, E. M.**, McDuff, D., Veeraraghavan, A. "Combining Magnification and Measurement for Non-Contact Cardiac Monitoring" *CVPR Workshops*, 2021
- 3. **Nowara, E. M.**, McDuff, D., "Warm Bodies': A Post-Processing Technique for Animating Dynamic Blood Flow on Photos and Avatars" *ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2021*
- 4. **Nowara, E. M.**, McDuff, D., Veeraraghavan, A. "A Systematic Analysis of Video-based Pulse Measurement from Compressed Videos" *Biomedical Optics Express*, 12.1 494-508, 2021
- 5. **Nowara, E. M.**, Marks, T. K., Mansour, H., Veeraraghavan, A. "Near-Infrared Imaging Photoplethysmography During Driving" *IEEE Tr1 ansactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems, 2020*
- 6. **Nowara, E. M.**, McDuff, D., Veeraraghavan, A. "A Meta-Analysis of the Impact of Skin Type and Gender on Non-contact Photoplethysmography Measurements" *CVPR Workshops*, 2020
- 7. **Nowara, E. M.**, Sabharwal, A., Veeraraghavan, A. "PPGSecure: Biometrics Presentation Attack Detection Using Photoplethysmograms." *Automatic Face and Gesture Recognition (FG)*, 2017

PATENTS

- 1. Marks T., Mansour H., **Nowara E.**, Nakamura Y., Veeraraghavan A., inventors; Mitsubishi Electric Corp, Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories Inc, assignee. "System and Method for Remote Measurements of Vital Signs of a Person in a Volatile Environment." *US Patent App. 17/199,696, 2021*
- 2. Marks T., Mansour H., **Nowara E.**, Nakamura Y., Veeraraghavan A., inventors; Mitsubishi Electric Corp, Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories Inc, assignee. "System and method for remote measurements of vital signs." *United States patent application* 16/167,668 2019

SELECTED AWARDS AND HONORS

•	Invited speaker, Microsoft Research AI Breakthroughs	2020
•	Best graduate poster and demo, ECE Corporate Affiliates Day at Rice University	2019
•	Ken Kennedy Institute for Information Technology Schlumberger Fellowship	2017 - 2018
•	Selected attendee, Doctoral Consortium at Automatic Face and Gesture Recognition	2017
•	Selected attendee, CRA-W (Computing Research Association) Grad Cohort	2016

LEADERSHIP AND MENTORSHIP

Vital Sign AI (startup volunteer project)

April 2020 - December 2020

Computer Vision and Machine Learning Research Lead, Remote

 Created a free app to measure vital signs remotely with cameras and microphones, and to detect abnormalities in vital signs caused by COVID-19

Reviewer August 2019 - Present

 Served as a reviewer for top tier computer vision, machine learning, and biomedical engineering conferences and journals, including CVPR, ICCV Workshops, AAAI, Face and Gesture Conference, Biomedical Optics Express, Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics

Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU)

Summers of 2016, 2020

Mentor, Rice University, Houston, TX

• Mentored undergraduate students in research projects in Computer Vision and Computational Photography